Alpha Society Records, 1878-1968
Smith College Archives
Alpha Society Records
1878-1968
Smith College. Alpha Society
RG 80 UUID:3a0efbe8-eca9-4add-92a1-ca944da19a97
4 boxes (1.66 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Alpha Society was Smith College's first literary society, formed in 1878, shortly after the opening of the College itself in 1875. The collection contains copies of an evolving constitution, programs of meetings and plays, letters, invitations, administrative records, meeting minutes, publications, and photographs.
Smith College's first literary society, Alpha Society, was founded by the Class of 1881 in the winter of their freshman year. Mary Sophia Wilkie chaired its first meeting on January 19, 1878. The Society soon gained much respect and admiration for its frequent productions of popular plays and its publication of its own newspaper, The Alpha. Members met approximately once every three weeks. The meetings included entertainment such as plays, music, readings, recitations, and lectures on various topics of interest.
Alpha Society was such a success that in 1892 five members broke off to form a rival society, Phi Kappa Psi. Both societies flourished, selecting their members by careful consideration of artistic merit and creativity. By 1934 student interests had shifted away from the arts. The two societies elected to combine into the society known as Alpha-Phi Kappa Psi, thus allowing both to endure.
In 1938 Alpha-Phi Kappa Psi adopted a new constitution which limited its membership to thirty students who had distinguished themselves in one or more of the arts. This reflected an ideological shift over the years from "an amusement society", as it was described by a member in 1883, to "an honorary [sic] society which recognizes outstanding creative achievement", as it was described in 1938. Activities of Alpha-Phi Kappa Psi were last recorded in 1968.
The collection includes materials from most decades of the existence of Alpha Society from the year of its founding in 1878, to its merger with Phi Kappa Psi in 1934 and subsequent transformation into an honor society, to its last year of record in 1968. The collection consists of copies of the Society's constitution, programs, song booklets, letters, dramatics and other student activities, photographs of members and officers, and publications. There are several items of note that highlight the evolution of the Society through the generations of its members and provide examples of the Society's contributions to the Smith College community.
All of the files are open to the public according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives.
Related materials found in Phi Kappa Psi Records.
- Series I: General 1878-1939
  Records and documents including a brief history of the Society, copies of its constitution and subsequent revised versions throughout its first decades, and membership lists. Correspondence with College administration and songbooks of Society lyrics set to contemporary music give an overall sense of its activities.
- Series II: Photographs 1889-1952, undated
  The bulk of the photographs are annual pictures of Society members. Some photographs are of a few members who were either officers or board members.
- Series III: Meeting Minutes and Notes 1878-1940 (Bulk 1878-1913)
  Four ledgers of Society meeting minutes and notes, from the first meeting held on January 19, 1878, to 1913, make up the bulk of the series.
- Series IV: Programs 1878-1916
  Programs of individual Society meetings customized on cardboard. Evolving through the first decades, they highlight artistic drawings that eventually gave way to a printed Alpha logo.
- Series V: Dramatics 1879-1947 (Bulk 1879-1916)
  Most plays in the series are identified by a single program or photograph. Of note is "A Modern Atalanta". Included are two handwritten drafts and two typewritten copies of the play, as well as three programs. As explained in the accompanying letter of February 7, 1947 by College Archivist Margaret Grierson, the play was written by Mary Mather '1883 about her roommate Elizabeth Lawrence '1883, who was the victor of the first tennis match played at the College. The play was not performed at the time it was written but was given as a birthday present after the two had graduated.
- Series VI: Publications 1879-1893
  The earliest publications of the Society are included. Alpha Paper was the first. Its first volume began with The Chip Basket, papers originally read before the Society. The Alpha and the The Alpha Quarterly are represented as well, as are the words and music of the 1879 play "H.M.S. Pinafore".
- Series VII: Alpha-Phi Kappa Psi 1934-1968
  The final series in the collection comprises three folders pertaining to Alpha-Phi Kappa Psi after the amalgamation of the two societies in 1934. Included is the constitution, membership lists, student activities, press board releases, correspondence, and photographs of the Society and its officers. Of particular note is the correspondence between the administration and faculty of the College and the Society in its later years in the 1950s and 1960s, as it struggled to maintain its viability as an honor society and made its final mark upon the historical record in 1968.
- Series I: General
  - Anniversaries 1888 (Box 3005)
  - Constitution 1879-1930 (Box 3005)
  - Executive Committee record of voting membership 1906-1908 (Box 3005)
  - Executive Committee record of "names vouched for" 1907-1916 (Box 3005)
  - Executive Committee record of "names on books" 1908-1922 (Box 3005)
  - History 1878-1939 (Box 3005)
  - Invitations 1881-1933 (Box 3005)
  - Membership List 1895-1933 (Box 3005)
  - Register 1898-1913 (Box 3005)
  - Songs undated (Box 3005)
  - Welcome Speech to New Members 1911 (Box 3005)
- Series II: Photographs
  - Photographs 1889-1900 (Box 3005)
  - Photographs 1901-1903 (Box 3005)
  - Photographs 1911-1914 (Box 3005)
  - Photographs 1916-1952 (Box 3005)
  - Photographs undated (Box 3005)
- Series III: Meeting Minutes and Notes
  - Minutes 1878-1891 (Box 3006)
  - Minutes 1891-1908 (Box 3006)
  - Agenda 1905-1906 (Box 3006)
  - Minutes 1907-1913 (Box 3006)
  - Pins and Awards 1940, undated (Box 3006)
- Series IV: Programs
  - Programs 1878-1879 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1885-1886 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1887 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1888 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1889 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1890 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1892-1893 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1894-1897 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1899-1900 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1904 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1907 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1908-1909 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1909-1910 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1910-1911 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1911-1912 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1912-1913 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1913-1914 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1914-1915 (Box 3007)
  - Programs 1915-1916 (Box 3007)
- Series V: Dramatics
  - "Nicholas Nickley" March 15, 1879 (Box 3007)
  - "H.M.S. Pinafore" May 10, 1879 (Box 3007)
    See also Box 3008
  - "Ellen and the King" May 10, 1879 (Box 3007)
  - "The Spanish Gypsy" January 17, 1880 (Box 3007)
  - "King Rene's Daughter" June 12, 1880 (Box 3007)
  - "The Fair Barbarian" 1881 (Box 3007)
  - "She Stoops to Conquer" c1881 (Box 3007)
  - 18821882 (Box 3007)
  - "A Modern Atalanta" November 11, 1884 (Box 3007)
  - "School" March 6, 1886 (Box 3007)
  - "A Plea for Amateurs" February 28, 1891 (Box 3007)
  - "Mock Trial" May 14, 1892 (Box 3007)
  - "Rip Van Wrinkle" April 21, 1900 (Box 3007)
  - "The Foresters" May 12, 1900 (Box 3007)
  - "At Twelve at Night" June 9, 1900 (Box 3007)
  - "Nance Oldfield" November 17, 1900 (Box 3007)
  - "A Box of Monkeys" January 19, 1901 (Box 3007)
  - "The Bird's Christmas Carol" January 23, 1901 (Box 3007)
  - "The Wheel of Progress" February 9, 1901 (Box 3007)
  - "Masks and Faces" March 23, 1901 (Box 3007)
  - "At the King's Head" April 27, 1901 (Box 3007)
  - Scenes from "Ingomer" May 18, 1901 (Box 3007)
  - "Grimm's Fairy Tales" November 19, 1901 (Box 3007)
  - "A Scrap of Paper" January 11, 1902 (Box 3007)
  - "Man Who Corrupted Hadley Burg" February 22, 1902 (Box 3007)
  - "Under the Beach Tree" February 23, 1907 (Box 3007)
  - "The Minet" 1916 (Box 3007)
- Series VI: Publications
  - Alpha Paper 1881 (Box 3008)
  - The Alpha 1890-1891 (Box 3008)
  - The Alpha Quarterly (Bounded) 1892-1893 (Box 3008)
  - The Alpha Quarterly (Unbounded) 1892-1893 (Box 3008)
  - "H.M.S. Pinafore" Words and Music 1879 (Box 3008)
- Series VII: Alpha-Phi Kappa Psi
  - General 1934-1968 (Box 3008)
  - Membership 1937-1968 (Box 3008)
  - Photographs 1937-1939 (Box 3008)